<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Belfry Upkeep</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/</link><description>Recent content on Belfry Upkeep</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/010-introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/010-introduction/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="introduction">
 Introduction
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#introduction">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="intro-title.jpg" alt="Allanconi bells at Hawkesbury, Gloucestershire" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Details of a bell installation are out of sight and out of mind for a surprising number of ringers but will soon be obvious if their upkeep is neglected. At the least, the bells may become progressively more difficult to handle, leading to poor striking, discouraging ringers and frightening away learners. At worst, it could result in expensive damage to the installation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Formal Requirements</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/020-permissions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/020-permissions/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="formal-requirements">
 Formal Requirements
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#formal-requirements">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>With very few exceptions, the bell ringers do not own the bells. There will usually be what we will term an &lt;strong>Authorising Body&lt;/strong> that will have a legal responsibility for the tower and its contents.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Steeple Keeper should be formally appointed by the Authorising Body in a clear, democratic, and traceable way, probably for a defined period of time. Once appointed, the Steeple Keeper should maintain contact with the Authorising Body at frequent intervals. While this applies to all ringers, it is particularly important for the Steeple Keeper because the operation and needs of a bell installation may not be familiar to the average member of an Authorising Body.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Faculty Jurisdiction Rules</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/030-faculty-rules/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/030-faculty-rules/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="faculty-jurisdiction-rules">
 Faculty Jurisdiction Rules
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#faculty-jurisdiction-rules">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="faculty-rules-title.jpg" alt="Leonard Stanley, Gloucestershire" />&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote class="book-hint danger">
 This chapter refers to activities carried out in churches within the jurisdiction of the Church of England. Ringers must remember that the Rules are set out in law, with possible penalties if they are not followed. Meeting the Rules is the responsibility of the Churchwardens and the Parochial Church Council, and ringers must use their specialist knowledge to assist the Church authorities in any application. Guidance should be sought from the Diocesan Secretary, The Diocesan Bell Advisor, and the local Guild or Association.
&lt;/blockquote>

&lt;p>Ringers are probably aware that a Faculty may be required prior to work being done in a Church of England Church. The faculty process exempts churches from listed building consent and conservation area consent that could apply elsewhere. When alterations are proposed, the parish must present the proposals to the archdeacon. For minor alterations, the archdeacon may authorise the work but more major projects will be judged by the Chancellor of the diocese, taking advice from specialists in the &lt;a href="../170-glossary/#diocesan-advisory-committee-dac">&lt;em>&lt;strong>Diocesan Advisory Committee&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. The faculty is the legal authorisation of the work by the Chancellor.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bell Frames</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/050-bell-frames/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/050-bell-frames/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="bell-frames">
 Bell Frames
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#bell-frames">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="frames_title.jpg" alt="Traditional timber frame" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bell frame is the structure which supports the bells. It fulfils several main roles:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It provides rigidity with an economy of materials and compactness&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It transmits the vertical and horizontal forces arising from the movement of the bells to the tower walls&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It provides a fair circle of ropes in the ringing room&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The design of bell frames has developed over the years as the need changed from simple chiming to full circle ringing, and as newer materials became available. The history is fascinating but outside the remit of this document. Here, we will describe the types of frames most likely to be encountered and the care which a Typical Steeple Keeper can provide in each case.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Headstocks</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/060-headstocks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/060-headstocks/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="headstocks">
 Headstocks
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#headstocks">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A headstock is one of the major structural elements of any bell installation, with each bell being hung from a headstock mounted on bearings on the bell frame. Each headstock carries the full weight of the bell during its rotation through just over a full circle, so they must be maintained in good condition.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Several other major parts of the installation are attached to the headstock:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Details of how the &lt;a href="../070-wheels">wheel&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="../080-stays-and-sliders">stay&lt;/a> are attached will be found in the relevant chapters.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Details of various ways in which the &lt;a href="../130-bells">bell&lt;/a> is attached are given in this chapter.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We also include here details of the attachment of the &lt;a href="../170-glossary/#gudgeons">&lt;em>&lt;strong>gudgeons&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, which fit into the &lt;a href="../100-bearings">bearings&lt;/a> to form the axle about which the bell rotates.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Headstocks were traditionally made of timber but, since the early 20th century, metal has been the most common choice. For the former, elm was frequently chosen because of its durability, but other hardwoods have been used. Metal headstocks can be cast iron or fabricated from steel.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Wheels</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/070-wheels/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/070-wheels/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="wheels">
 Wheels
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#wheels">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The basic design of bell wheels has changed little over the past 200 years. The arrangement of the spokes is both traditional and functional, although there may be some variations. A wheel is made in two parts to allow it to be fitted around the headstock. This has the bonus of making it easier to manoeuvre the parts up to the bell chamber.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="naming-of-parts">
 Naming of Parts
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#naming-of-parts">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A typical wheel is constructed from eleven different components, some with different historic names. Figure 1 shows a typical wheel, viewed as it would be seen with the bell ‘down’. The names used in this chapter, with some alternatives in brackets, are identified on Figure 1 as follows:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stays &amp; Sliders</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/080-stays-and-sliders/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/080-stays-and-sliders/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="stays--sliders">
 Stays &amp;amp; Sliders
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#stays--sliders">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="s-and-s_title.jpg" alt="Broken stay" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &lt;strong>Stay&lt;/strong> is a mechanism which allows a bell to be ‘parked’ (the ringing term is ‘&lt;strong>Set&lt;/strong>’) with its mouth upwards. This is achieved by the stay engaging with a &lt;strong>Slider&lt;/strong>, which allows the bell to go just past the point of balance in either direction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The stay also acts as a ‘safety valve’. It is designed to break if the bell is set too violently, avoiding damage to other, more expensive, parts of the installation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Clappers</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/090-clappers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/090-clappers/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="clappers">
 Clappers
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#clappers">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="title.jpg" alt="Clapper in motion" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This chapter covers:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#background">Background&lt;/a>: The various types of clappers, how
they are made and suspended within the bell&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#checking">Routine Checking&lt;/a>: The ways in which clappers can
be checked, both as part of a routine maintenance schedule and to
investigate any problems&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#maintenance">Maintenance&lt;/a>: The options for dealing with
problems and the level of experience needed to carry them out&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Final sections cover: &lt;a href="#other">Other Information&lt;/a> relevant to
clappers and &lt;a href="#further">Further Reading&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="background">
 Background
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#background">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A clapper assembly comprises four main components:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bearings</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/100-bearings/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/100-bearings/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="bearings">
 Bearings
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#bearings">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The main bearings are critical items: in any installation, they support the large mass of metal swinging through a full circle and their condition is fundamental to the ‘go’ of the bell. You may encounter the two types of bearing – plain bearings and ball bearings. We will describe both, but a Typical Steeple Keeper’s main task will be the important role of carrying out the checks described here. This will help identify any problems before they reach a critical stage.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rope Routes</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/110-rope-route/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/110-rope-route/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="rope-routes">
 Rope Routes
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#rope-routes">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="rope-routes_title.jpg" alt="Rope Guide at Leonard Stanley" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The rope may encounter many obstacles between the bell and the ringer. The main reasons are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It is difficult to design a traditional rectangular &lt;a href="../050-bell-frames">bell frame&lt;/a> with all ropes falling in a perfect circle, especially with constraints on space and the possible need for a two-tier frame.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There may be obstacles such as support girders, ladders and clock cases which limit the placement of ropes.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Any obstacle to free movement of the rope will have an effect on the handling of the bell. In this chapter we describe situations which a Steeple Keeper may encounter and the implications for checking and fixing problems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bells</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/130-bells/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/130-bells/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="bells">
 Bells
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#bells">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="title-bells.jpg" alt="Bell lit from the side" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bells are important as the public voice of the church – familiar to those living near or passing by. Made of cast bronze (an alloy of about 77% copper and 23% tin), they have been associated with English churches since at least the seventh century. The oldest surviving bells date from about the twelfth century, although these are rarely part of a ring of bells. However, it is not unusual to find a pre-reformation (pre-1534) bell still in use.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Maintenance Schedule</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/150-maintenance-schedule/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/150-maintenance-schedule/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="maintenance-schedule">
 Maintenance Schedule
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#maintenance-schedule">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The maintenance schedule is an important document:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It defines what items need regular checking and how often.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It includes provision for recording the results, including any remedial work carried out or still outstanding.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It provides evidence that the schedule has been observed in case of any incidents.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This chapter includes a model schedule and reporting sheets for download and modification to suit the needs of your tower, and guidance on how that modification can be carried out.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fault Finding</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/160-fault-finding/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/160-fault-finding/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="fault-finding">
 Fault Finding
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#fault-finding">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="common-problems-with-bells">
 Common Problems with Bells
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#common-problems-with-bells">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This &lt;a href="static/SM_CommonProblems_2021_v3_1.pdf">downloadable PDF&lt;/a>, originally produced as a separate document on the Central Council website, offers a way of identifying some of the more common faults with bells and indicates how they may be solved. The difficulty and urgency of each diagnosis is indicated by codes, along with a guide to permissions which may be required before work is carried out (based on the &lt;a href="https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/030-faculty-rules">Faculty Jurisdiction Rules&lt;/a>). Less experienced Steeple Keepers should consult the relevant chapter(s) in this document before attempting to carry out any work.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Glossary</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/170-glossary/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/170-glossary/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="glossary">
 Glossary
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#glossary">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>As with any technical subject, bell ringing and bell hanging has, over the years, developed specialist terms some of which are unique to ringing and others which have particular meaning when applied to ringing. Some other technical terms may not be familiar to ringers. We hope to have included all of these here. They are linked from the text in the various chapters. Items appearing elsewhere in the glossary are shown in &lt;strong>Bold&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Acknowledgements &amp; Sources</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/180-acks-and-sources/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/180-acks-and-sources/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="acknowledgements--sources">
 Acknowledgements &amp;amp; Sources
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#acknowledgements--sources">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This chapter lists the people who have contributed, in various ways, to this document, and the sources which have been consulted.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="acknowledgements">
 Acknowledgements
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#acknowledgements">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Production Software&lt;/strong>: &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo&lt;/a> Static Site Generator, &lt;a href="https://github.com/alex-shpak/hugo-book">Book&lt;/a> Theme.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>For technical advice&lt;/strong>: Bryn Reimer, Mark Elvers, Lucas Williams and Graham John.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>For words, pictures, reviews, comments and general assistance&lt;/strong>: Tina Andrew, David Bagley, John Beresford, Marcus Booth, Will Bosworth, Keith Brown, Dave Clark, Graham Clifton, Tony Crabtree, Alan Frost, Alison Hodge, James Joynson, Roger Lawson, Ernie de Legh-Runciman, Julia Lysaght, Robin Milford, Alan Moult, Allen Nunley, John Payton, Chris Pickford, Chris Povey, Philip Pratt, Mark Regan, Simon Ridley, David Roskelly, Robin Shipp, Malcolm Taylor, Aveline Perez de Vera, Andrew Ward, Peter Woollam.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Avian Influenza</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/040-health-and-safety/avian-flu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/040-health-and-safety/avian-flu/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="appendix-cleaning-bell-chambers-contaminated-with-bird-waste-or-carcasses">
 Appendix: Cleaning Bell Chambers Contaminated with Bird Waste or Carcasses
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#appendix-cleaning-bell-chambers-contaminated-with-bird-waste-or-carcasses">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="with-reference-to-avian-influenza--bird-flu">
 With reference to avian influenza / bird flu
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#with-reference-to-avian-influenza--bird-flu">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Birds finding their way into towers, particularly bell chambers, has been an issue that ringers have had to deal with and try to prevent for as long as bells have been hung in towers. I find it interesting to think that back in the 1300&amp;rsquo;s some monastery servant, sexton or local labourer would have been tasked with climbing the tower with a sack and a shovel to remove sticks, nests and carcasses just as I have done. The sack would have been made of sackcloth not polyethylene, but otherwise it&amp;rsquo;s a shared human experience that links my life with one perhaps 30 generations ago.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rope Driers</title><link>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/120-ropes/rope-driers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://belfryupkeep.cccbr.org.uk/docs/120-ropes/rope-driers/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="appendix-rope-driers-for-bell-towers---some-suggestions">
 Appendix: Rope Driers for Bell Towers - Some Suggestions
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#appendix-rope-driers-for-bell-towers---some-suggestions">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Ringers may wish to use a ‘rope drier’ to reduce stiffness in bell ropes that become damp in an unheated ringing room. Driers are usually designed and assembled by volunteers. However, questions have been raised about some of the rope driers that have been seen during checks and inspections of churches and towers. For non-ringers, it is not immediately evident what the units are used for or how they are to be used. Being electrical equipment fitted with a mains power plug, the concern is reasonable.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>