<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Docs on Devon Call Changes</title><link>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/</link><description>Recent content in Docs on Devon Call Changes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction</title><link>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/010-introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/010-introduction/</guid><description>Introduction # This book is going to be quite a personal account of learning and developing call change ringing in the Devon style. I hope that by reading it you will see that ringing call changes in the way they ring them in Devon and the South West, or more particularly the focus on call changes as a performance rather than just as a transition step before moving to method ringing, could be good for your band.</description></item><item><title>The Ultimate Goal</title><link>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/015-ultimate-goal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/015-ultimate-goal/</guid><description>The ultimate goal # Devon call change ringing done well is a mesmerising sound. There is a continuous stream of notes which is not interrupted by the open handstroke lead that method ringers insert. It is also said that the ringing of bells slightly below the balance generates a different sort of sound to method ringing where the bells go to the balance and stop for longer.
As I think it is always good to see what you are aiming at, here are a selection of videos of call change ringers in action.</description></item><item><title>Chapter 1 - They’re different down there</title><link>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/020-down-there/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/020-down-there/</guid><description>Chapter 1 They’re different down there # As you have probably gathered, call change ringing is a feature of ringing in the South West of England – Devon and Cornwall specifically. These counties are not in a different country – you can visit them without a passport. If you do visit them, you may come across call change ringing in the style I am trying to explain in this book, so it is worth giving you a few notes and tips to prepare you for your experience.</description></item><item><title>Chapter 2 - First Principles</title><link>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/030-first-principles/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/030-first-principles/</guid><description>Chapter 2 First Principles # There are a few things that set Devon calls apart from the sort you are used to.
Closed handstoke leads! # OK, so some of your ringers probably ring with closed handstroke leads anyway and you have given up telling them about it. A perfect open handstroke lead is actually quite difficult to achieve, and what is perfect anyway? You may be told to leave a whole bell’s gap, but actually about three quarters of a bell’s gap sounds OK.</description></item><item><title>Chapter 3 – Getting Started</title><link>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/040-getting-started/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/040-getting-started/</guid><description>Chapter 3 – Getting Started # In this chapter I am just going to talk about getting the band ringing rounds with a closed handstroke lead. Even this is quite an exhilarating thing to do and should be your first target. So the treble’s handstroke will strike straight after the tenor’s backstroke has struck and there should be no way of telling which is the handstroke and which is the backstroke without looking.</description></item><item><title>Chapter 4 - A few call changes</title><link>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/050-call-changes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucasjwilliams.github.io/callchanges/docs/050-call-changes/</guid><description>Chapter 4 – A few call changes # Once you have mastered the basic rhythm of ringing rounds with a closed handstroke lead it is time to introduce some call changes. In this chapter we are going to watch a call change peal that is 16 changes long and quite logical. It introduces the principles of 60 on 3rds without going too far. This call change peal will be the target.</description></item></channel></rss>